<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Earnest perswasion vnto the pastours of Christes churche, whersoeuer thei be dispersed, but especially vnto his Churche of Englande that as thei haue thruste the plough share into the grounde, so zelously and watchfully to walke forth right, not leanyng to the left hande, neither tournyng to the right, for who so laieth hold of the plough and looketh backe, is not apte for the kingdome of heauen.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19781.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23232519</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23232519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26417</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26417)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1802:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Earnest perswasion vnto the pastours of Christes churche, whersoeuer thei be dispersed, but especially vnto his Churche of Englande that as thei haue thruste the plough share into the grounde, so zelously and watchfully to walke forth right, not leanyng to the left hande, neither tournyng to the right, for who so laieth hold of the plough and looketh backe, is not apte for the kingdome of heauen.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1580]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26417:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26417:1"/>
            <p>¶ An earneſt perſwaſion vnto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours of Chriſtes Churche, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thei be diſperſed, but eſpecially vnto his Churche of Englande: That as thei haue thruſte the Plough ſhare into the grounde, ſo ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly and watchfully to walke forth right, not leanyng to the left hande, neither tournyng to the right. For who ſo laieth hold of the plough and looketh backe, is not apte for the kingdome of heauen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26417:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26417:2"/>
            <head>To the chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et no man that ſhall reade, or heare this reade, or any thing within this booke conteined, thinke or imagine the writer hereof is perſwaded, or goeth about to perſwade, by any woorde, within this booke, that it were meete or conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for any Preacher or Miniſter, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct vnto hymſelf, either cappe or other garmente: but that thei are all bounde by the duetie of their alleagance, to weare and doe, all ſuche orders as the Prince ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct them, to imitate and followe: or els with ſainct Peter, by the worde of God, to confuce the ſame, as neither lawfull nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. And not by their euill example, ſuffer the truthe to be ſhadowed and darc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, the forwarde fathers to bee by the Papiſtes, condempned as raſhe and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed doers. But either to proue them ſo, or els to defende their quarell, and be content to bowe their ſholders to the bearyng of the croſſe, the whiche who ſo refuſe to doe
<pb facs="tcp:26417:3"/>ſhalbe founde loyterers, and not true la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers. To whom theſe fewe woordes are dedicated and directed, I truſte none other thyng then by the ſincere truthe, maie bee ſufficiently ſupported and defended. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you not to eſteme this to bee dooen of arrogancie, neither to haue any ill mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, but onely to craue at your handes; ſome ſhorte pitthie woorke to ſatiſfie all men. For a great nomber of the laite will in no wiſe now goe backe to their old leſſons, [beyng now further and muche better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed] then to defile theim ſelues with the giltines of this crime: to the condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of all thoſe reuerende fathers, whiche haue followed the Apoſtles; in the puritie of perfecte religion, receiued from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue churche. But deſire rather to ſteppe forwarde ſtill, vntill it ſhall pleaſe God to baniſhe al ſuperſticion clene out of this churche, whiche he ſone bring to paſſe for his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake. Amen, AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26417:3"/>
            <head>¶ The voyce of GOD <hi>vnto his Churche.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Rapped in wofull wiſe,</l>
               <l>with dolefull dolours depe:</l>
               <l>In ſobbing ſighes &amp; trillyng teares</l>
               <l>halfe wakyng halfe a ſlepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Methought I heard the voice,</l>
               <l>of God whiche thus did ſaie:</l>
               <l>Vnto his paſtors of this churche,</l>
               <l>Awake it is clere daie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You maie not ſlumber now,</l>
               <l>nor walke as in the night:</l>
               <l>Ye muſt doe the worke of the daie,</l>
               <l>whiche now ſhines faire and bright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(Why) haue ye hardned hartes,</l>
               <l>let them be molified:</l>
               <l>Why will you wafte and wauer ſtilt,</l>
               <l>ſtande faſt and doe not ſlide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beware thou wauer not,</l>
               <l>and wafte with euery winde:</l>
               <l>Steppe forward ſtill and ſtagger not,</l>
               <l>be not ledde by the blinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou haue ſtepte a wrie,</l>
               <l>to ſtarte backe is no ſhame:</l>
               <l>If in the plaine pathe thou dideſt walke,</l>
               <l>walke forthe right in the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:4"/>
               <l>Let not the worldly pompe,</l>
               <l>be vnto you a yoke:</l>
               <l>Clenſe all your groundes and ſuffer not,</l>
               <l>the thornes my wheate to choke,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(<hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that valiaunt wiſe capitaine:</l>
               <l>Whoſe noble actes, the Romaines olde,</l>
               <l>in greate renoume retaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beyng offered the Croune,</l>
               <l>refuſyng (it) he ſaied,</l>
               <l>Moche more honour then happineſſe,</l>
               <l>vnto the croune is teide,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſaied) who knewe the charge,</l>
               <l>and eke the cares moſte greate,</l>
               <l>Would not voucheſafe to take it vp,</l>
               <l>findyng it in the ſtreate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Muche leſſe honour to holde,</l>
               <l>whereby he ſhould ſtande bounde:</l>
               <l>Not (onely) his owne conſcience,</l>
               <l>but others to confounde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Prophetes all are ſuche,</l>
               <l>as will in no wiſe like:</l>
               <l>That ye ſhould wander in by waies,</l>
               <l>as one that weare to ſeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When ye did firſt profeſſe,</l>
               <l>to fauour myne eſtate:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26417:4"/>
you vowed then with feruent harte,</l>
               <l>my lawes to celebrate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when your wanton toyes,</l>
               <l>wherein you tooke ſolace:</l>
               <l>Had cauſed me to caſt you of,</l>
               <l>and tourne from you my face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When for your iuſte deſertes,</l>
               <l>I ſemed to ſet you light:</l>
               <l>Suffryng your fooes, to ſpread the fieldes,</l>
               <l>with banners of deſpight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when your Godlie guides,</l>
               <l>for your dealynges vniuſte:</l>
               <l>Were troden doune defaced eke:</l>
               <l>and ſome conſumed to duſte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then could you call and crie.</l>
               <l>then could you make greate mone:</l>
               <l>Then if I would become your frende,</l>
               <l>you would (ſerue) me alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then all adulterous waies,</l>
               <l>ye would deteſt and hate:</l>
               <l>Promeſſe you made (not to pollute)</l>
               <l>my houſe in any rate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You ſaied you would be ſeen,</l>
               <l>in no wanton attire:</l>
               <l>But that you would reformed be,</l>
               <l>as I ſhould beſt require.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:5"/>
               <l>But all to ſone I ſee,</l>
               <l>you haue forgotte this geare:</l>
               <l>You are become wilde Calues againe,</l>
               <l>you are not as ye weare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If for obedience,</l>
               <l>you ſeme to tourne that waie:</l>
               <l>And are content to pleaſe mennes mindes,</l>
               <l>and my will diſobeye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In this you haue doen ill,</l>
               <l>thus to famiſhe my flocke:</l>
               <l>To feede thoſe bealie Gods that of,</l>
               <l>you make a laughyng ſtocke,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I would that you ſhould not,</l>
               <l>offende my little ones:</l>
               <l>Nor dandlyng thus your diſſemblers,</l>
               <l>daſhe myne againſt the ſtones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(Oh) why doe ye deuiſe,</l>
               <l>to make my waies more darcke:</l>
               <l>And force my flocke to ſlippe backwarde,</l>
               <l>when thei would hit the marke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My little cilie Lambes,</l>
               <l>whom ye ſhould feede and cheriſhe:</l>
               <l>By bryngyng in this geare againe,</l>
               <l>thei are now like to periſhe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What your conſcience will doe,</l>
               <l>that thei doe moſte abhorre:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26417:5"/>
And ye condempne my true preachers,</l>
               <l>as though thei ran to farre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereby you doe aduouche,</l>
               <l>the Papiſtes whiche doe ſaie:</l>
               <l>Some runne to ſlowe, and ſome to ſwift,</l>
               <l>in them there is no ſtaie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But walke ye forwarde ſtill,</l>
               <l>and I will them perſwade:</l>
               <l>Thei can not winne the garlande ſo,</l>
               <l>excepte thei deeper wade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Suche are ne whot ne colde,</l>
               <l>like them thei would you weare:</l>
               <l>But of their filthie cuppe drincke not,</l>
               <l>it is to bitter geare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſhalt commit no ill,</l>
               <l>that good maie happe thereby:</l>
               <l>And yet thou art become ſo blinde,</l>
               <l>thou ſeeſt not thy folly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But tourne to me thine eare,</l>
               <l>and liſten to my lore:</l>
               <l>No newe founde toye I will thee tell,</l>
               <l>but that hath been before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some little ones I haue,</l>
               <l>that ſo farre for the are growne:</l>
               <l>That ſuffer will moſte greuous paines,</l>
               <l>to haue myne honour knowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:6"/>
               <l>Your waies are not my waies,</l>
               <l>your thoughtes are not like myne:</l>
               <l>Not you but I worke my one workes,</l>
               <l>yet not as you define.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſome deſpiſed ones,</l>
               <l>my honour for the I ſpredde:</l>
               <l>For thei are of my choſen churche,</l>
               <l>whereof I am the bedde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not all the worldly wiſe,</l>
               <l>but ſome ſuche as appere:</l>
               <l>Moſte ſimple to the wicked worlde,</l>
               <l>thoſe are my children deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You muſte talke francklie now,</l>
               <l>it is no tyme to flatter:</l>
               <l>We maie not here looke for greate ſheanes.</l>
               <l>but rake in thoſe that ſcatter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The harueſt is nere doen,</l>
               <l>but yet the ſtubble is ſtoute:</l>
               <l>Wherein lieth hid many good eares,</l>
               <l>whiche ye muſt now glein out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You muſt diſpatche in haſt,</l>
               <l>that all were in my Barne:</l>
               <l>Harueſſ is doen, Winter drawes nere,</l>
               <l>ſaie that I you doe warne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Myne Angell crieth out,</l>
               <l>vnto the Harueſt manne:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26417:6"/>
Thruſt in thy Title on the yearth,</l>
               <l>prepare the Flaile and Fan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For now throughout the yearth,</l>
               <l>their graine is ripe out right:</l>
               <l>The floure muſt forthewith be clenſed.</l>
               <l>and all chaffe blowen out quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Spurne not againſt the pricke,</l>
               <l>my worke finiſhe I will:</l>
               <l>The dotyng age of this old worlde,</l>
               <l>would lye and loyter ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is no tyme to gape<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>or gaſe for pollecie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>For what I haue determined<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>that ſhalbe doen quicklie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore my Harueſt men,</l>
               <l>ſet to your Sithes with ſpeede:</l>
               <l>For thoſe that I finde loyteryng now,</l>
               <l>I will caſt out as weede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke not your ſwift cuttyng,</l>
               <l>ſhall cauſe one graine to fall:</l>
               <l>For I haue counted euery eare,</l>
               <l>not one corne periſhe ſhall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You maie ſette forthe your ſelues,</l>
               <l>and ſeme to further me:</l>
               <l>Truſting your wiſedomes more then mine</l>
               <l>but ſo it would not be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:7"/>
               <l>You might doe your good willes,</l>
               <l>and truſt me with the reſt:</l>
               <l>You might doe what I you commaunde,</l>
               <l>and not what you thinke beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As tymes there are to ſpeake,</l>
               <l>and tymes to be ſilent:</l>
               <l>In ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>in my workes be feruent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What good ſeruaunt thinke ye,</l>
               <l>in this caſe could be ſlacke:</l>
               <l>That for one foote forewardes would now,</l>
               <l>ſeme to ſteppe twoo foote back<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not talkers but walkers,</l>
               <l>in my harueſt are meete:</l>
               <l>Not reſpecters but directers,</l>
               <l>of my rites are moſte feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not daundlers but handlers,</l>
               <l>of my worde without cloke:</l>
               <l>Not ſuche as feare, but as will beare,</l>
               <l>my ioyfull croſſe and yoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now note what ye haue ſeen,</l>
               <l>in my ſteppes and that doe:</l>
               <l>But doe not ſeme to helpe my workes,</l>
               <l>by addyng yours thereto.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For what haue I to doe,</l>
               <l>with you, or your aduice;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26417:7"/>
In their due tymes I doe all thynges,</l>
               <l>to purpoſe moſte propice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I knowe there is no prince,</l>
               <l>that takes my worde in hande:</l>
               <l>But will heare you and be content,</l>
               <l>to haue the truthe well ſtande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to the mercifull,</l>
               <l>if you feare truthe to tell:</l>
               <l>What would you then to tyrauntes doe,</l>
               <l>that are bothe fearce and fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Daniell in denne,</l>
               <l>laye deſtitute of aide:</l>
               <l>How came Abacucke into hym,</l>
               <l>how were the Lions ſtaied.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Ionas in the ſea,</l>
               <l>who did prouide the Whale:</l>
               <l>And preachyng vnto Niniue,</l>
               <l>who did preferre his tale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What hope had Abraham:</l>
               <l>when he did imolate:</l>
               <l>At my requeſt his ſonne Iſaac,</l>
               <l>how ſtoode then his eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And what was Iacobs hope,</l>
               <l>ſeruyng his ſier Laban:</l>
               <l>You knowe well how his cace did ſtande,</l>
               <l>and how I holpe hym than.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:8"/>
               <l>Of Ioſeph in Egipte,</l>
               <l>and of his father olde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>What I wrought for them in that lande<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>long tales might here be tolde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Papiſtes looke to haue,</l>
               <l>miracles at your hande<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>What miracles might you haue wrought</l>
               <l>in this realme of Englande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lions mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thes you might,</l>
               <l>haue ſtaied and ſtopped faſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The blinde and lame reſtored to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>and made your foes agaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why did you not as I,</l>
               <l>example did ſhewe here:</l>
               <l>What Paule receiued, that he gaue,</l>
               <l>his plaineſſe d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> app<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now you knowe my minde.</l>
               <l>let this faulte be amended:</l>
               <l>And ſcorne not at this ſhort warnyng.</l>
               <l>for ye haue ſore offended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I knowe all fleſhe is fraile,</l>
               <l>and verie prone to fall:</l>
               <l>To ſtarte backe when you ſtep <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miſſe,</l>
               <l>it is no ſhame at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſe how loth you were,</l>
               <l>to doe that you haue doen:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26417:8"/>
And eke how ſore you doe lament,</l>
               <l>that euer it begonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be not ſlacke to confeſſe,</l>
               <l>nor ſlowe to tourne again.</l>
               <l>Since you doe knowe my will, doe it:</l>
               <l>let me not preache in vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As ended were theſe wordes:</l>
               <l>me thooght the planettes ſeuen,</l>
               <l>Did leſe their light and ſtreames of blood,</l>
               <l>tell forthwith doune from heauen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereby the yearth enfecte,</l>
               <l>greuous plagues did enſue:</l>
               <l>What I haue heard and ſeen ye knowe,</l>
               <l>Gods peace be now with you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tell you what I heard,</l>
               <l>and eke what I haue ſeen:</l>
               <l>The Angelles of almightie God,</l>
               <l>defende our noble Quene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe mightie maieſtie,</l>
               <l>preſerue her grace from ſmarte.</l>
               <l>And powre his ſpirite plentifully,</l>
               <l>into her noble harte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He graunt her his good will,</l>
               <l>that ſhe as willyngly:</l>
               <l>Maie hym embrace, and bend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her harte,</l>
               <l>to baniſhe all Poperie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26417:9"/>
               <l>The euer (beyng) God,</l>
               <l>graunt this as I haue praied:</l>
               <l>Amen, Amen of eche good harte,</l>
               <l>ſo be it now be ſaied.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
